Guide to the New-York Historical Society Geographic Images Collection circa 1600-2006 PR 20
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: New York City Views - Manhattan
  - Subseries IC: MANHATTAN - FLAT MATERIALS- PHOTOS
    - Manhattan - Flat Material - Photos - Buildings
      - Clubs, Societies and Associations -A-L (Folder FF346)
        Liederkranz Club
      - Clubs, Societies and Associations -M-Z (Folder FF347)
        Manhattan Athletic Club
        Masonic Hall
        National Academy of Design
        Player's Club
        Road Driver's Association of New York
        Tammany Hall
        Union Club
        Union League Club
        University Club
        YMCA, 23rd Street and Fourth Avenue
      - Commercial & Financial -Banks (Folder FF348)
        Bank of New York
        Bowery Savings Bank
        Colonial Bank
        Dry Dock Savings Bank
        Merchant's Bank
        (Drexel) Morgan & Co.
        Nassau Bank
        National Park Bank
        Tradesman's National Bank
      - Commercial & Financial -Exchanges (Folder FF349)
        Consolidated Stock Exchange Cotton Exchange X New York Stock Exchange
      - Commercial & Financial -Insurance Companies (Folder FF350)
        Equitable Life Insurance
        Hartford Accident Insurance Company
        Manhattan Life
        Metropolitan Life
        New York Life Insurance Company
      - Commercial & Financial -Markets (Folder FF351)
        West Washington Market
      - Commercial & Financial -Office buildings A-B (Folder FF352)
        One Wall Street
        American Express Building
        Bordon Building, 350 Madison
        Broaker & Schmidt, Public Accountants, 63 Fifth Ave. (interiors)
      - Commercial & Financial -Office buildings C-F (Folder FF353)
        City Investing Building
        Corbin Building, John & Broadway
        Empire State Building
        Exchange Court Building, Exchange Place
        Flatiron Building (under construction)
        Fox Office Building & Studios, Tenth Ave. & 55th St.
      - Commercial & Financial -Office buildings M-S (Folder FF354)
        Mercantile Building, 122 Fifth Avenue
        New Trust Company. 39 Wall Street
        St. Paul Building
        Singer Building
        Stockbroker's office interior 30 Broad Street
      - Commercial & Financial -Office buildings T-Z (Folder FF355)
        United Nations
        Washington Building, 1 Broadway
        Woolworth Building
        World Trade Center
      - Commerical & Financial -Stores and Shops (Folder FF356)
        A. T. Stewart's Dry Goods
        De Pinna Store, Fifth Avenue at 52nd St. 1956
        William P. Howell, Gunpowder Agent, 205 Front St
        R.H. Macy, Dry Goods
        Traphagen, Hunter & Co. Clothiers, 398 Bowery
      - Government- General (Folder FF357)
        Barge office on Battery Place
        Castle Garden immigration station
        Custom House [Federal Hall National Monument] on Wall Street
        Custom House on Bowling Green
        Federal Office Building, 90 Church Street
        New York County Courthouse
        Second Circuit Court of Appeals
      - Government -City Hall in City Hall Park (Folder FF358)
      - Government -Fire Department (Folder FF359)
        157 East 67th Street-Engine Company 39, Hook and Ladder Company 16.
        Engine Company 33
        Fire Patrol 1
        Engine Company 9.
      - Government -Post Offices (Folder FF360)
        Post office, Broadway and Park Row
        Post office, Seventh Avenue and 32nd Street.
      - Government -Prisons (Folder FF361)
      - Hotels A-E (Folder FF362)
        Hotel Albert
        Hotel Bellclaire
        Bennett House
        Hotel Brunswick
        Clarendon Hotel
        Continental Hotel
        Hotel de Ashe
        Hotel Earle
      - Hotels - Hotel Empire (Folder FF363)
      - Hotels F-H (Folder FF364)
        Fort George Hotel
        Gilsey House
        Grand Hotel
        Holland House
      - Hotels - Gotham Hotel (Folder FF364.5)
      - Hotels I-L (Folder FF365)
        Hotel Imperial
        Hotel Knickerbocker
        Knott Hotels Group
        Hotel Lafayette
        Hotel Lucerne
        Lafayette Place Hotel
      - Hotels M-N (Folder FF366)
        Hotel Marie Antoinette
        Hotel Marlborough
        Hotel Martin
        Mount St. Vincent Hotel
        Murray Hill Hotel
        National Hotel
        Hotel Navarre
      - Hotels - Plaza Hotel (Folder FF367)
        Plaza Hotel
      - Hotels Q-Z (Folder FF368)
        Hotel St. Andrew
        Hotel Savoy
        Sinclair House
        Spingler House
        Hotel Touraine
        Hotel Victoria
        Walton House
        Windsor Hotel
      - Hotels - Waldorf Astoria (Folder FF369)
      - Institutions - Hospitals and Asylums (Folder FF370)
        Bellevue Hospital
        Charity Hospital (Blackwell's Island)
        Floating Hospital
        Hospital for the Ruptured and Crippled
        House of Mercy
        Presbyterian Hospital
        St. Joseph's Orphan Asylum (formerly Nathaniel Prime mansion), East 89th Street
      - Libraries (Folder FF371)
        Lenox Library
        Mercantile Library (under construction)
        New York Public Library, 42nd and Fifth (under construction)
      - Museums (Folder FF372)
        Eden Musee
        Guggenheim Museum
        Metropolitan Museum of Art (including interiors)
        Museum of Natural History
        New-York Historical Society
      - Manufacturers & Warehouses I (Folder FF373)
        Brewster & Co, Carriage Works
        Daniel Coger & Son, ship joiners, 480 Water St.
        Eagleson & Deveau Vermont Marbleworks, 427 W. 14th St.
        Irving & Son Carriage Factory, 118 W. 52nd St.
        Monahan's Xpress Company Depot, W.11th St. and 7th Ave
        Ben Moral, shoe manufacturer, 566 Broadway
        Nason Manufacturing Co., 71 Beekman St.
        Rhinelander Sugar House
        Steinway Piano warehouse
        Unidentified cigar factory, interior with workers
      - Manufacturers & Warehouses II (Folder FF374)
        Fairchild Bros. & Foster, manufacturing chemists, office interiors
        Unidentified hardware manufacturing firm
      - Manufacturers & Warehouses - Knickerbocker Storage Warehouse (Folder FF375)
        interiors and exteriors. Located on East 24th Street.
      - Monuments - General (Folder FF376)
        Christopher Columbus Monument
        Horace Greeley Statue
        Sherman Statue (Central Park)
        Statue of Liberty
      - Monuments - Dewey Arch (Folder FF377)
      - Monuments - Grant's Tomb - General, 1887 and later (Folder FF378)
        includes dedication ceremonies
      - Monuments - Grant's Tomb - First building, 1885-1886 (Folder FF379)
      - Monuments - Grant's Tomb - Decoration Day, 1922 (Folder FF380)
      - Monuments - Washington Arch (Folder FF381)
        includes temporary arch on Fifth Ave. and permanent monument in Washington Square Park.
      - Printers & Publishers (Folder FF382)
        Great American Printing Co., Beekman St. ca. 1871
        New York Herald, Broadway and 35th St. 1895
        New York Times, Park Row and Nassau St. 1872-73
        New York World
        New York World Telegram, 125 Barclay St.
        News Building, 216-236 42nd St.
      - Residences A-E (Folder FF383)
        Abeel, John H., 127 Second Ave
        Audubon, John James, ca. 1912
        Bicknell, Frank Albert (studio interior)
        Brainerd, C. N., Kingsbridge Rd.
        Carnegie, Andrew (art gallery)
        Carrigan, Andrew, 114th St. and Riverside Dr.
        Cudlipp, Joseph, Broadway and 76th St.
        DeWitt, Peter, 11 St. Marks Place
      - Residences - Apthorpe, Charles Ward, West 91st Street (Folder FF384)
      - Residences - Astor, Mr. William (Folder FF385)
      - Residences - Babcock, Hamlin. On the East River between E. 75th and E. 76th Street (Folder FF386)
      - Residences - Boker, Carl F., 23 W. 76th Street, circa 1909 (Folder FF387)
        interiors
      - Residences - Bradhurst estate, W. 148th Street and St. Nicholas Avenue (Folder FF388)
      - Residences - Codwin, Elliot C., 18 West 21st Street (Folder FF389)
      - Residences F-H (Folder FF390)
        Fabri, Ernesto, 11 E. 62nd St.
        Gerry, Commodore Elbridge T., E. 60th St. and Fifth Ave.
        Goelet, Peter, 19th St. and Broadway
        Griswald, William E.S., 883 Fifth Ave. (interior)
        Harsen, Jacob, Tenth Ave. and 70th St.
      - Residences - Gracie Mansion - exteriors (Folder FF391)
        includes images by Pach Bros. photographers
      - Residences - Gracie Mansion - interiors (Folder FF392)
        mainly taken by Pach Bros. photographers ca. 1890
      - Residences - Grenzebach, John N., Third Avenue and East 75th Street - interiors (Folder FF393)
      - Residences - Hamilton Grange (Folder FF394)
        Estate of Alexander Hamilton, 143rd. Street and 10th Avenue, Harlem. Includes interiors, and a series of exterior photos from 1874.
      - Residences - Hammond, John Henry, 9 East 91st Street - interiors (Folder FF395)
      - Residences - Havemeyer, Theodore A., 244 Madison Ave. at 38th Street- interiors (Folder FF396)
      - Residences - Herbert, J. W., 835 Fifth Avenue - interior and exterior, 1913 (Folder FF397)
      - Residences - Huntington, Collis P., 57th Street and Fifth Ave. (Folder FF398)
      - Residences I-M (Folder FF399)
        Jones, Mary Mason, 1 East 57th Street (Marble Row)
        Kuttroff, Adolph, 17 E. 69th St.
        Leary, Countess Annie, 1032 Fifth Ave. (interiors, including dining room set for a Columbus Day dinner party)
        Meyer, John, farmhouse, Eighth Ave. and 133rd St. before 1877
        Mott, Jordon and Winifred, W. 54th St
      - Residences - James, Arthur Curtiss, 39 E. 69th St. - interiors (Folder FF400)
        includes two photos of household staff dressed in livery and wigs. Also includes photos by Johnson-Hewitt Studio, Matties Edwards Hewitt's first firm
      - Residences - Klopsch, Louis and Mary, 100 East 17th Street - interiors (Folder FF402)
        Louis Klopsch was the publisher of the Christian Herald. He and his wife lived in an apartment on the 6th floor of the building at 100 East 17th Street.
      - Residences - Marquand, Henry G., 11 East 68th Street - interiors (Folder FF403)
      - Residences - Morris-Jumel Mansion (Folder FF401)
        includes a photograph of Eliza Jumel and her family on the porch ca. 1860
      - Residences N-R (Folder FF404)
        Prime residence, foot of E. 89th St., 1904
        Pyne, Percy R., 680 Park Ave., 1911
        Richards, Augustus C., Fort Tryon Park
      - Residences - Parish, Daniel, 2 East 16th Street - interiors (Folder FF405)
        photographs signed "Pach N.Y."
      - Residences - S (Folder FF406)
        Schley, Grant B., 812 Madison Ave. (interiors)
        Schubert, Henry, 203 W. 125th St.
        Schwab, Riverside Dr. and 73rd St.
        Shaw, Samuel T., 41 W. 74th St. (interior)
        Sloane, Henry and Jessie, 7 E.72nd St.
        Smith, Bartlett, Washington Heights
        Stewart, A. T., 34th St. and Fifth Ave.
        Striker, Garrit Hopper
      - Residences - Schuyler, George L., Gramercy Park - interiors (Folder FF407)
        photos stamped "Alley & Co., N.Y."
      - Residences - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Madison Ave. - interiors (Folder FF408)
        photos signed "Ludovici's Studio, 889 Broadway"
      - Residences T-V (Folder FF409)
        Talmar, John H., West 68th Street and West End Avenue
        Tiffany, Louis Comfort, Madison Ave. and East 72nd Street
        Tileston, Thomas, 2 East 14th Street (interiors)
        Townsend, Samuel P., Fifth Ave. and 34th Street
        Varian, George W., Sixth Ave. and 28th Street
      - Residences- Van Beuren, Michael Murray, 21 West 14th Street - interiors (Folder FF410)
        photos by Pach Bros., 935 Broadway, New York
      - Residences- Vanderbilt, Cornelius, 1 West 57th St. - exterior and interior (Folder FF411)
        Most interior photos signed "Pach Photo N.Y."
        Exterior photo by J.S. Johnston, 1894.
      - Residences - Vanderbilt, William K., 660 Fifth Ave. - exterior and interiors (Folder FF412)
        Exterior is an artotype by Bierstadt.
      - Residences - Vanderbilt houses, Fifth Avenue (Folder FF413)
        3 Townhouses ["The Triple Palace"] 640 & 642 5th Avenue and 2 West 52nd Street
        Home to: William Henry Vanderbilt, I [1821-1885]
        Margaret Vanderbilt [Mrs. Elliott Fitch] Shepard [1845-1925]
        Emily Vanderbilt [Mrs. William Douglas] Sloane [1852-1946]
      - Residences W - Z (Folder FF414)
        Ward, John, 8 Bond St. (interiors)
        Ward, Libbeus B., 59th St. and Tenth Ave.
        Watt, Thomas, W. 139th St
        Wilkes, Charles, 49th St. and Tenth Ave.
        Wright, Charles C., 70 W. 26th St.
        Villard Houses, 457 Madison Avenue
      - Residences - Ward, William G., 14 Carroll Place - exterior and interiors (Folder FF415)
        Carroll Place is now Bleecker Street
      - Residences - Whitney, William C., 68th Street and Fifth Avenue - interiors, 1901 (Folder FF416)
        Photos by Davis & Sanford, N.Y. and by H.H. Sidman, 8 East 42nd Street, N.Y.
      - Residences - Apartment houses- General (Folder FF417)
        425 Riverside Dr. (floorplan)
        Dakota, 72nd St. and Central Park West
        London Terrace, 23rd St. and Ninth Ave
        Stevens' House, 27 Broadway
      - Residences - Apartment houses - New Mariner's Home, 43 Cherry Street (Folder FF418)
      - Restaurants and Taverns- General (Folder FF419)
        Alt Heidelberg, 130 Third Ave.
        Cedar Jack's Clam Bar
        Herman Handel's Lagerbier House and Restaurant
        Keen's Chop House, 36th St.
        Louis Martin's Cafe
        Mori Restaurant
        Nassau Café and Restaurant, 33rd St.
        Whyte's Restaurant, 143 Fulton St.
      - Restaurants and Taverns - Fraunces Tavern (Folder FF420)
        includes photographs by Wurts Bros. and George P. Hall and Son
        contains 3 images of a Sons of the American Revolution 4th of July Parade, 1912.
      - Schools & Colleges A-Z (Folder FF421)
        City College of New York (CCNY)
        Cooper Union 1865
        Homeopathic Medical College
        Hunter College
        Manhattan College
        New York Academy of Medicine
        Packard Commercial School
        Public School #177, 46 Monroe Street
      - Schools & Colleges - Columbia University (Folder FF422)
        includes photos by Irving Underhill. Also includes artotypes by Bierstadt of the unveiling of the tablet commemorating the Battle of Harlem Heights. Ceremony took place at Columbia University on October 16, 1897. Tablet, erected by the Sons of the Revolution, was placed on the Engineering Building.
      - Schools & Colleges - Graham School, 176 West 72nd Street - exterior and interiors, 1893 (Folder FF423)
        also known as The Misses Graham's School for girls. (Boarding and day school)
        Related Materials
        The N-YHS Library holds a copy of the Graham School's Agora Centennial Yearbook 1816-1916. F128 LD7501.G73 A46 1916
        Agora Centennial Yearbook
      - Sports Stadia - Polo Grounds (Folder FF424)
      - Theaters A-L (Folder FF425)
        Academy of Music, 14th St.
        Booth's Theatre, Sixth Ave. and 23rd St.
        Broadway Theatre, at Broome St.
        Casino Roof-Garden
        Chickering Hall, Fifth Ave. and 18th St.
        Daly's Theatre, Broadway and 30th St.
        Eagle Theatre, Sixth Ave. and 32nd St.
        Fourteenth Street Theatre
        Globe Theatre, Broadway and Waverly Pl.
        Grand Opera House, Eighth Ave. and 23rd St.
        Hammerstein's Olympia Theatre, Broadway and 44th St.
        Hippotheatron (New York Circus), 14th St., 1865
        Hudson Theatre, 139 W. 44th St
      - Theaters M-L (Folder FF426)
        Metropolitan Opera House
        New York Circus, 1865
        New York State Theater, Lincoln Center
        Niblo's, Broadway and Prince St. (including interior)
        Olympic Theatre, Broadway and Bleecker St.
        Star Theatre, Broadway and 13th St.
        Town Hall
        Wallack's Theatre, Broadway and 13th St.
      - Theaters - Carnegie Hall (Folder FF427)
      - Theaters - Madison Square Garden (Folder FF428)
        Includes photos of three different buildings. Also contains a series of photos by Wurts Brothers documenting the Stanford White-designed Madison Square Garden, including one of the building being torn down.
      - Buildings- Other- Richard Canfield's Gaming Hall, 5 East 44th Street - interiors (Folder FF429)
        photos by Wurts Bros. Photo N.Y.C.
    - Manhattan - Flat Material - Photos - Transportation
      - Elevated Railroads - Third Avenue (Folder FF430)
      - Elevated Railroads - Sixth Avenue (Folder FF431)
        includes photos of the El being torn down.
      - Elevated Railroads - Ninth Avenue - Powelson photographs (Folder FF432)
        Series of nine photographs of the Ninth Avenue El taken by Gustavus A. Powelson in 1876.
      - Elevated Railroads - Ninth Avenue (Folder FF433)
      - Elevated Railroads - Ninth Avenue - 110th Street Curve (Folder FF434)
      - Elevated Railroads - Locomotives (Folder FF435)
      - Elevated Railroads - Stations (Folder FF436)
        includes: 34th St. Station, Third Ave. line
        Battery Park/South Ferry Terminal, Sixth and Ninth Ave. lines
        14th St. Station, Sixth Ave. line
        33rd St. Station, Sixth Ave. line
      - Street Railroads (Folder FF437)
      - Subway (Folder FF438)
        includes: subway construction photos
        Two photos of the ground breaking ceremony for the Rapid Transit Tunnel, part of a moving picture filmed by the American Motoscope and Biograph Company circa 1901.
      - Transportation Stations - Ferry Terminals and Piers (Folder FF439)
        includes: Cunard Steamship Co., Pier 40
        Fulton Ferry Terminal
        White Star Line, Pier 45
        Unidentified pier interiors
      - Transportation Stations - Grand Central (Folder FF440)
        includes images of Grand Central Depot (1871, extensively renovated and renamed Grand Central Station in 1900) and Grand Central Terminal (1913).
      - Transportation Stations - Pennsylvania Station (Penn Station) (Folder FF441)
        includes photos of construction and interiors.
      - Transportation Stations - General (Folder FF442)
        includes:
        Fourth Avenue Depot (32nd St.)
        New York Central Freight Station frieze
        Port Authority Commerce Building/Union Inland Terminal #1 under construction
        The pier shed of the Pennsylvania and B & O Railroads at Pier 21, South Street.
    - Manhattan - Flat Material - Photos - Utilities
      - Utilities - General (Folder FF443)
        includes Broadway Outlet Sewer, 1905
        Croton Reservoir, 1898, by Geo. P. Hall and Son
        Water main at 110th Street, 1900
        East 74th Street Powerhouse
      - Utilities - Hydrants and Standpipes (Folder FF444)
        color photos.
    - Manhattan - Flat Material - Photos - Events
      - Blizzards (Folder FF445)
        includes images of the Blizzard of 1888 and Blizzard of 1947.
      - Celebrations - General (Folder FF446)
        Yorktown Celebration, 1883
        Hudson River Railroad Centennial, 1951
      - Celebrations - Columbian Quadricentennial, 1892 (Folder FF447)
      - Fairs (Folder FF448)
        includes: American Institute Fair, 3rd Avenue and 63rd Street, 1873
        Crystal Palace, 42nd Street and 5th Avenue, 1854
        Metropolitan Sanitary Fair, 643 Park Ave.
      - Fires (Folder FF449)
        Broadway and Ann Street fire, 1971
        Equitable Building fire, 1912
        Park Theater fire, 1882
        Roosevelt Building fire, 1903
        Trinity Place fire, 1971
        Windsor Hotel fire, 1899
      - Funerals (Folder FF450)
        includes funeral of Phillip Milledolor, 1852 (photograph of painting)
        Ulysses S. Grant funeral procession, 1885
        Unidentified funeral at St. Paul's Church
  - Subseries ID: MANHATTAN - OVERSIZE MATERIAL
    - Manhattan - Oversize Prints - Bird's Eye Views
      - New York in 1849, engraved by S. Weekes after E. Purcell, published by Robert Sears (Folder OS FF 500)
      - New York from the Steeple of St. Paul's Church, engraved by Papprill after John William Hill, 1849 (Folder OS FF 501)
        Six copies, some marked "proof"
      - Bird's Eye View of New York & Brooklyn, C. Matter, lithographer, printed by I. Schaerer., circa 1852 (Folder OS FF 500)
      - Bird's Eye View of the City of New York, Presented to the Subscribers of the Illustrated News, Nov. 26 1853, engraved by Frank Leslie after Charles Parsons (Folder OS FF 502)
        Three copies
      - Panorama of Manhattan Island, City of New York and Environs, John Bornet, lithographer, published by Goupil, 1854 (Folder OS FF 500)
      - New York, from the Latting Observatory, engraved by William Wellstood after Benjamin F. Smith, published by Smith, Fern and Co., 1855 (Folder OS FF 503)
        Two copies
      - City of New York, drawn on stone by C. Parsons, lithographed by Nathaniel Currier, 1856 (Folder OS FF 504)
      - New York und Umgegend, engraved by R. Kupfer, printed by H. Peters, 1867 (Folder OS FF 505)
      - The City of New York, published by Currier & Ives, 1870 (Folder OS FF 504)
      - The City of New York – Showing the Building of the Equitable Life Insurance Society of the United States, published by Currier & Ives, 1876 (Folder OS FF 504)
      - New York and Brooklyn, drawn on Stone by Parsons and Atwater, published by Currier & Ives, 1877 (Folder OS FF 504)
      - The Port of New York, Bird's Eye View from the Battery, Looking South, Parsons and Atwater, del., published by Currier & Ives, 1878 (Folder OS FF 504)
      - New York in 1886, drawn by John R. Chapin, engraved by the Illustrated News, Cincinnati (Folder OS FF 506)
        supplement to the Cincinnati Illustrated News, Grand Holiday Number, Christmas 1886.
      - Greater New York, Charles Hart, lithographer, published by E.M. Parsons., 1897 (Folder OS FF 506)
      - King's Bird's Eye View of Greater New York, drawn by Richard W. Rummell, originally published by Moses King, 1904 (Folder OS FF 507)
        Re-published by the Lawyer's Title Insurance Company of New York as "New York City in 1904 - Bird's Eye View of the Five Boroughs Forming Greater New York"
      - Greater New York, Charles Hart, lithographer, published by Joseph Koehler, 1905 (Folder OS FF 506)
        Four copies
      - [Bird's Eye View from New York Harbor], Richard Rummell, del., published by Detroit Publishing Co., 1911 (Folder OS FF 507)
    - Manhattan - Oversize Prints - Composite Views
      - Excursion Through New York City in Two Hours! -broadside advertising Bullard's Panorama of New York City, circa 1857 (Folder OS FF 508)
        includes multiple vignettes of NYC buildings and sights, highlighting Bullard's Panorama.
      - The Empire City, Presented to Subscribers to the History of the City of New-York [multiple views of the city], Arthur Lumley, del., 1859 (Folder OS FF 508)
      - Downtown District of Manhattan - Nieuw Amsterdam and New York, 1789-1939, drawn by A. Zaidenberg (Folder OS FF 508)
        map showing building and street names, as well as notes and illustrations of historic sites, events, and figures.
    - Manhattan - Oversize Prints - General Views
      - Novelty Iron Works, Foot of 12th St. E.R. [East River] New York, J. Penniman, del., printed by Endicott's Lithography, circa 1841-1844 (Folder OS FF 509)
      - The Washington Stores in William Street, between Fulton and John Streets, G. and W. Endicott's Lithography, circa 1845 (Folder OS FF 509)